Orson S. Keyes Correspondence
Orson S. Keyes Correspondence
1853-1866
Keyes, Orson S.
0.25 linear ft.
Correspondence (77 letters) to, from, or about Orson S. Keyes, Private, 5th New York Volunteers. Also a few photographs.
2741995
Biographical History
Orson S. Keyes (1838-1864), of Cattaraugas County, New York, was a private with the 5th New York Volunteers during the American Civil War. He was taken prisoner during a skirmish near Culpeper, Virginia on September 13, 1863 and died in prison on April 19, 1864.
Scope and Contents of the Collection
The Orson S. Keyes Correspondence consists of 77 letters and a few photographs.
Letters are to and from Orson S. Keyes and his family and friends. One, dated 3 July 1863, was written "near Gettysburg, Pa" and describes the battle then in progress: "Gen. Sickles was brought in a few minutes ago wounded in the leg." There are also comments on camp life (e.g., "I have yet to see the officer who does not use liquor," 1 Jul 1863) and other matters. The collection also includes a few earlier letters from Keyes to his parents, written from Lima, New York, and a few letters written by friends or family after Keyes' death.
One folder of Photographs -- of Keyes, of his uncle Daniel J. Keyes, and of Foster Dickinson, possibly a relation by marriage -- complete the collection.
Arrangement of the Collection
Letters are in alphabetical order by correspondent.
Subject and Genre Headings
Military history; New York State; Civil War (U.S.); Dickinson, Foster.; Keyes, Daniel J.; Keyes, Franklin.; Keyes, Orson S.; Keyes, Peter Jr.; United States. -- Army. -- New York Infantry Regiment, 5th (1861-1863); United States -- History -- Civil War, 1861-1865 -- Personal narratives.; Soldiers -- New York (State) -- Cattaraugus County -- Biography.; Correspondence.; Photographs.; Soldiers.
Access Restrictions
The majority of our archival and manuscript collections are housed offsite and require advanced notice for retrieval. Researchers are encouraged to contact us in advance concerning the collection material they wish to access for their research.
Acquisition Information
Gift of Janet Graham, 1965.
Inventory
- Letters
  - About Keyes, 1863-1864 (Box 1)
  - Blossom. John, 1863; 1866 (Box 1)
  - Dickinson, Foster, 1862-1863 (Box 1)
  - Foster, Jane, 1863 (Box 1)
  - Keyes, A. F., 1862; 1864 (Box 1)
  - Keyes, Daniel, 1862-1863; 2 folders (Box 1)
  - Keyes, Orson S., 1853; 1858,; 1861-1863; 2 folders (Box 1)
  - Keyes, Peter, 1862 (Box 1)
  - Unidentified, 1863-1864 (Box 1)
  - Miscellaneous envelopes (Box 1)
- Photographs
  - Miscellaneous, Orson S. Keyes, Daniel J. Keyes, Foster Dickinson; 7 items (Box 1)